I feel like I want to start with saying
that
we've seen a lot of agents in the last
few years and in a lot of ways we've
solved building agents.
But this talk is not about the first
iteration of when you get an agent
running in in your laptop. It's about
how do you really deploy them at scale
reliably
and sort of up-level the agents that
we're building.
Um
the reason I'm talking about this as
Adam alluded to is that I've been
building an ML infra for for about 5
years. Um even more if you count the
previous company I was doing it at. Um
and at ZenML what we did was we built ML
ops um infrastructure and ML pipelining
infrastructure for orchestrating machine
learning workloads.
Which funnily enough ML ops has a lot of
things that that are shared
with AI or agent ops. Um
and like having seen that industry play
out in the way it has, um I feel like
there's a lot of things that we could
just learn and shortcut in the in the
agent era. So
so that's what I'm here to talk about.
Um maybe perhaps we should really start
with
taking a step back and seeing how far
we've come with
with agents. Um
the capability is obviously real. Like
like some of the examples here are just
cherry-picked. Uh we've been tracking
this in the ZenML LLM ops database. So
there's a link over there. If you're
interested, we have thousands of
cataloged use cases.
Um it's also an MCP server if you want
to check it out and pull it in your
local
um machine
where we really go through all the
published case studies in the world of
how agents run.
And one thing is for sure real is that
in the last 3 months especially we've
seen a massive uplift of what these
things can do.
So, the capabilities indeed very real,
at least in some certain instances.
So, why isn't it really
that everybody around us is talking
about long-running ambient agents all
the time
in enterprise? So, so that's that's
really the question, right? So,
numbers like these are thrown thrown
around
a whole bunch of the time. You can take
them with a with a grain of salt. I'm
sure some of you are running agents at
scale
in your companies.
But, the fact is that if you really zoom
out from from a global GDP perspective,
there's still no real measurable P&L
impact
of gen AI projects in the enterprise.
And
like no matter if you want to see how
many are in production or if you want to
see how many projects have been
canceled,
so even though we know that there is a
lot of capability that exists in a few
companies have really up-leveled and
up-skilled themselves to get to that
scale,
the
the fact is that the production
infrastructure and the tooling and
what's required to operate them at scale
really hasn't got up yet. And and that's
just a fact
given given all the data that we see.
And we see that in the
in our own databases with the ZenML
LLMOps database that I referred
to as well.
So,
perhaps we can dig one layer deeper into
why
why exactly does the enterprise
struggle? And I feel like one of the
things that's important to understand is
the recent progress that has happened
with agents, especially in the last 3
months, let's say roughly around the New
Year's time and then open claw
has largely been driven by longer
running agents which have worked
autonomously.
You can see this in the meter
like one of our favorite metrics to look
at is how long can can an agent do a
task with a certain probability of
success
and and and how long
does such a task take? And you can see
that that's growing exponentially still.
So this curve I've been talking about
this for
around 1 and 1/2 years and it's it's
it's it's been steady. So it's it's very
predictable how that goes.
But the thing is
these long-running agents,
what we've discovered recently
is most of them are software agents,
coding agents. So
I'm pretty sure all of you are using
coding agents.
And the fact is that coding is sort of
an expression of math, which is a
representation of reality. And
and if you if you zoom really out, you
can see that you can achieve a lot of
tasks
with code, expressing code that you
normally wouldn't associate perhaps
directly with codes. For example, if you
want to build a presentation like I did.
So this presentation is built through
cloud code.
You can do that with code. So you the
agent should write code.
It should execute the HTML and then
deploy it, for example.
There's many other tasks that you
wouldn't necessarily have associated
with code directly. But we found out
through harnesses like cloud code that
actually these general agents tend to be
very good coding agents.
So
so that's just one thing to note.
These longer-running agents tend to be
very good at coding. LLMs are very good
at coding.
And that generalizes.
And then what seems to have happened
is we seem to be coining terms every few
months in this space. Um
There has been a collective realization
that oh, it's not the model that's
driving that
advancement. It's the harness. Right,
what is the harness? Well,
I'm pretty sure if I talked to every one
of you
the
the definition might slightly vary, but
but let's put it this way. If there's a
while loop where you ask an LLM
something and it says execute a few few
few tool calls, then the system that
actually executes those tool calls,
manages the memory, does the context
engineering,
does all the things that Open Claw was
very good at, for example, is what we're
collectively referring to as the
harness. Let's simplify it accordingly.
And you can see that since November
we've been talking about this a lot. And
like one thing I found very interesting
was
actually this
a research engineer by the name of Chan
Boluk who actually got from 6.7%
accuracy to 68.3 accuracy in in his
coding tasks by building just a local
coding agent.
And all he did was he changed the edit
format of the harness,
which he didn't have control over when
he was using Cloud Code or GPT Code X.
Which is a very interesting example of
how you can make now very simply your
own personal harness that optimizes for
your task, and it can give you massive
massive gains.
And you can see this with Open Claw,
right? The acquisition of Open Claw
or
I saw Modal Book was acquired a few
hours ago that's by Facebook. So so
there's obviously a push from
from a lot of the foundational models
labs to go up the stack towards the
harness.
So
which sort of reminds me a little bit of
the bitter
truth like the bitter pill to swallow.
If there's anything we've learned in the
last 3 years of agents and LLMs is that
the foundational model tends to consume
a lot of the harness as we go along
because the model labs are
doing their evals accordingly.
So for example
last year if you were talking about
fine-tuning for tool calling, tool
calling, now you don't need to do that
anymore because the models have taken
that over and they're very good at tool
calling now.
So
what I started thinking about recently
is
we're sort of in this loop of we
constantly have to rewrite the harness
because the underlying layer gets better
and gets consumed into the harness. So,
I like the example of Manos, for
example, Manos had five rewrites of
their entire harness in 6 months because
every time a new model came out, they
had to rewrite that whole assumptions
they made because they just went out the
window.
Um we had like similar thing with deep
agents with LangChain.
Vercel, um they just realized if they
took away 80% of their tools in their
harness, it just got better.
So, really I think the lesson to learn
is if you over-engineer the control flow
um of
of the harness, you might end up losing
because the model just will get better
and might eat up all of your
assumptions.
So,
if anything, one thing you should
probably take away from this talk is the
prompt structure, the control flow, the
tools formats, uh you might want to
innovate on them and learn about them
and tinker,
but really you should expect the model
providers to get a lot better
uh as time goes. Um so, you might not
want to innovate on that.
But, here's the thing.
That is not the only thing the harness
consists of. And this might be
controversial,
but for me there's a model-facing layer
of the harness.
So, imagine the model layer is the
the the thing that interfaces with the
model, the thing that manages some of
the context, some of the uh assumptions
you made about
around tool calling, um
how you do tool calls, how you do the
message formats.
Those things are probably things like
recursive language models might eat
those things up.
But, one thing I can almost guarantee
that won't get eaten up is the
infrastructure layer, so the the
world-facing layer. The thing that goes
when you actually deploy the model
outside of your local machine.
Right now,
I think we're very used to running cloud
code in our
in our in our local machines and for for
us this is a huge win.
And that's fine because
I think that already up level so many
people and cloud code is not just a
coding agent. It's a general agent as as
we learned.
But where the world is headed is pretty
obvious.
You don't want this tied to your
machine.
So you don't want if I close this
machine right now your agents and your
sub agents just stop.
So you actually want to get it out of
your machine
into some other system and then you want
to have a system around orchestrating
all of that.
And really I think that system has gone
is is probably pretty under developed in
the agent world.
So
that part of the harness is probably
something you could innovate on and
could invest in as leaders in your
company because I think that's going to
be increasingly important in the next
few years.
So
if you want to run a fleet of agents
it doesn't really scale like linearly.
So it's very easy to go from one agent
to 10 to hundreds to thousands because
it just makes sense to scale it that
way. You have companies like Spotify,
Stripe and Cursor doing this already.
So it's fascinating to me to see
Stripe is
merging thousands of PRs which are
purely developed with with agents which
are running in an ambient environment.
It's like background agents. They're not
running in a local machine. They're
they're driven through events that are
sourced
um and are running at scale and it's
really working in production. So
what ends up happening
is this is just it comes back down
to the fact that this is a distributed
systems problem.
Um
you you have to manage lots of
microservices which are stateful.
Um and you have to do this at scale. And
you have to make sure that this robust
and reliable and execute things exactly
once.
So how do you actually build this layer?
Like,
what is the
Like, what are your
Like, today, what are your choices as
enterprise leaders
or in your company to build this layer?
So, I think there's really two
choices you have.
We have option A, which is you build it
yourself. Um Stripe did it.
Perhaps you can as well.
Um and the other option, which I feel
like is pushed with the model
foundational app companies, is they're
hiring FTEs. So, they're they're sort of
hiring forward deployed engineers
because they know that their harness
needs to be deployed on onto some
infrastructure that's bespoke to the
enterprise, and they want to take that
back into their company. So, they're
incentivized to do that. So,
I believe they hired 800% more forward
deployed engineers. I'm talking about
OpenAI. Uh in the last 8 months than
they did the 8 months before that. And
that's going to keep increasing.
But, the the fact is that when these
FTEs go home, who maintains and builds
this layer? So,
my instinct is having seen this story
before in the last 5 years in ML Ops,
is that you'd sort of need a function
inside your company that owns the
internal platform that orchestrates
these agents. Because that knowledge,
you would be astounded at how much gain
and how much differentiation you can
make with your competitors if you have a
function that's dedicated and build into
that. And I'm pretty sure in the future,
or even if it's not happening today, AI
platform layers that handle those things
are going to be built bespoke in a lot
of enterprises.
Like Stripe did.
Cool. So,
good news.
Um we have
multiple decades now of cloud compute
and uh knowledge from the world of
DevOps, then ML Ops, now we're going
towards whatever Ops.
Um there's a few new primitives which
I'd like to highlight. So, I think
orchestrating agents,
perhaps durable execution is more
important.
Observability, things like BrainTrust or
LangFuse or just OTEL OTEL traces are
important. Governance, identity.
But the two things which are pretty much
unique to agentic workloads on the
infrastructure side are perhaps the
memory side
and the sandboxes side. So,
if we believe in the fact
that
agents which are good in general purpose
are good coding agents, then probably
you don't want them to execute arbitrary
amounts of code
in their local
host machine.
So, things like Monty,
like from the Pydantic team, or things
like Data Owner or E2B are getting
increasingly relevant. And this is why
you see a lot of funding going into that
because it feels like this that's a
central primitive
to enable ambient agents that run
autonomously for long amounts of time to
execute code in a safe way.
So,
these
these primitives
right now exist almost in silos.
And they're not being talked about in a
composable
easy to grok way.
And this is my appeal to everybody here
today
that we should probably as a collective
industry start talking about this
problem. Because we've done this with ML
Ops. We had so many things like feature
stores, model registries, experiment
tracking, deployment targets, central
central ways of standardizing what a
model was.
We don't have any of these things for
agents right now. We don't have a
central place of serializing an agent. I
know the Pydantic team is trying and we
should we should support them
especially in open source, but there's
so many things around standards that we
need to build that probably build on top
of the previous standards that we'd
already built.
So, my appeal to everybody here today
is let's collectively start talking
about the infrastructure layer of the
harness more than just the other model
side layer, which it seems to be
dominating social media.
Um
so
if I was to sum it up
the model is going to be an API call.
The framework will probably get
replaced.
But the infrastructure is the only thing
that will compound and is probably worth
investing in today in 2026.
Um and a small announcement, so this is
a little plug.
So, because we've been thinking about
this for so many years
we're actually building a tool that is
taking all of the knowledge we had with
ML ops
with ZenML
and we're working on making a composable
layer
for building
your AI infrastructure layer in a
composable stack inside your enterprise.
If you're interested, we're looking for
early testers. This is This is very new.
So, the project's name is Kitaru,
uh which means to arrive somewhere in
Japanese.
Um and there's a little QR code
at the bottom right here
or even here if you want to scan it. Um
or you can just grab me in the
conference floor. I'd love to talk about
the primitives of building the next
generation of AI infrastructure
platforms um for agents.
Thanks for your attention. Thank you.
>> Uh do we have questions for Hamza?
>> You drew the analogy. I'm I'm Sudhir
from Hydrotek. Uh you drew the analogy
with microservices. Um
and then uh if you think about
microservices, Kubernetes,
orchestration, and it kind of grew up
from
um
but the microservices when they talk to
each other, they're kind of pre-wired
endpoints and application protocol in
this seven-layer stack. We we don't seem
to have any standards on the
I mean I haven't looked at deep into
agent to agent. But if if you could talk
about where you see it going with agent
decides on the fly to I need to talk to
these other agents and that knowledge
therefore can easily talk to the
authentication authorization all the
other issues we
that we orchestrated virtual machines
and all that they're kind of back up
again, but there seem to be any apart
from your talk I haven't seen
discussions that have focused on that.
So if you can talk about that that'll be
great.
>> Yeah,
I mean it's a great question. The
the primitives we need the standards we
need to build as you said are quite new.
So things like agent to agent and even
if you look at things like MCP are
probably good efforts in that direction.
I haven't seen A to A really take off in
production although I've seen some of
our customers use it.
Um I don't know whether that is the end
all and be all of communication protocol
between agents. But one thing I do think
is wrongly categorized a lot in
infrastructure world is that agents are
just microservices because
in many ways microservices were
are built to be stateless and agents are
very stateful
by design. So there's a context there's
a memory that you need to preload into
them.
Um and also the latency requirements and
and things like that are quite different
in in agents because I mean if you think
about it if the LLM takes multiple
seconds to think about something it
doesn't really matter some of the
assumptions we had for running 150,000
transactions for durable execution for
microservices.
Um so again, we're very we're very
early. Um I don't know what the protocol
will be but this was sort of my attempt
at um trying to motivate
uh this sort of discussion because
as you said I haven't seen enough of
that. But I do feel like whatever we're
going to build on is probably going to
be uh shortcutted with the 20 years of
experience of running microservices at
scale uh which is classic software.
Um so I'm I'm really looking forward to
the time we standardize that.
>> Thank you for the great talk. Um
I think you accurately like described
some of the key pillars of building
agent infrastructures.
Uh the sandboxing space is interesting.
Like there's not a lot of open source
projects. I've been like thoroughly
reviewing, seeing what's happening on
GitHub. Um like there are different
patterns also. Like do you run your
agent inside a sandbox or you have an
agent running somewhere in a central
place and using many sandboxes? Um are
there
things that you've experimented with
that you want to share like early
findings and what do you think will
happen in sandboxing space?
>> This is a very good question. So, um
there is no like I feel like there's two
patterns, right? Either you run the
agent within the sandbox
and then
or either you give the sandbox as a
primitive as a tool to the agent, right?
Uh I was yesterday at the Daytona
compute conference where I had
conversations around this and it feels
like
the pattern is 50/50.
So, sometimes it makes sense to run the
agent itself in the sandbox. Um
sometimes it doesn't. I don't feel like
that's something we should worry about
too much because it's probably always
going to be dependent on the use case
and probably you might want to mix and
match. But one thing I am really
interested in nowadays is sandboxes
comes from the world of infrastructure
which is ephemeral.
So, most of the sandbox services for
example don't run sandboxes more than 24
hours.
And they're just designed around that.
And now open claw sort of taught us
that we don't need ephemeral
instances. Perhaps we just need a
computer, a real computer for this thing
with a real identity attached to it
that's just doing things and editing
state
um on the fly and you want to give it
more powers, right? So, for me the
pattern that I'm not sure about yet is
whether we are going to be
innovating on
having ephemeral storage
uh for for sandboxes that just take
snapshots from the memory and from the
file system in such an efficient way
that that just becomes trivial. So, you
can just fork and do replays and all
that. Or, whether we're going to
gravitate as an industry towards these
like fully Mac Mini sort of setup where
you just buy it and it's just there and
it's just running.
Um,
so I'm not I'm not super sure about
that part that pattern yet. I think it's
still emerging.
Thank you so much for your attention,
everybody.
>> Let's thank Comdex again.